Multi-Layer Secure Network Lab
Defense-in-Depth Security Architecture
Top-level design:
WAN, LAN, and OpenVPN
pfSense at the center
Lab nodes:
pfSense, Ubuntu Server, VPN Client, Kali Linux
Firewall layer:
Block Telnet, SMB, RDP, FTP
Default deny posture
OpenVPN layer:
Authenticated remote access
Secure LAN connectivity
Snort IDS/IPS:
Detect scans, abnormal traffic, and attack patterns
Host hardening:
UFW, fail2ban, auditd, SSH restrictions
Monitoring and response:
Loki, Grafana, syslog-ng, auto-response
Validation scenarios:
Nmap scan, SSH brute force, light flood test
Result:
Layered security improves detection,
prevention, and response